<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.28.0-wmf.16</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2600" case="first-letter">Topic</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Politics</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>22986</id>
    <revision>
      <id>735389478</id>
      <parentid>735245903</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-08-20T11:13:55Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Yobot</username>
        <id>7328338</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>clean up / fix section header naming ([[WP:ASL]]) using [[Project:AWB|AWB]] (12082)</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="44888">{{other uses}}
{{geographical imbalance|date=July 2014}}
{{Politics}}
'''Politics''' (from {{lang-grc-gre|πολιτικός ''politikos''}}, definition &quot;of, for, or relating to citizens&quot;) is the process of making decisions applying to all members of a group. More narrowly, it refers to achieving and exercising positions of [[governance]] — organized control over a human community, particularly a [[State (polity)|state]]. Furthermore, politics is the study or practice of the distribution of power and resources within a given community (a usually hierarchically organized population) as well as the interrelationship(s) between communities.

A variety of methods are deployed in politics,   which include promoting  or forcing one's own political views among people, [[negotiation]] with other political subjects, making [[law]]s, and exercising [[force (law)|force]], including [[warfare]] against adversaries. Politics is exercised on a wide range of social levels, from [[clans]] and [[tribes]] of traditional societies, through modern [[local government]]s, [[company|companies]] and institutions up to [[sovereign state]]s, to the [[international politics|international level]].

It is very often said that politics is about power.&lt;ref name=&quot;Political Geography&quot;&gt;{{cite web|last1=Painter|first1=Joe|last2=Jeffrey|first2=Alex|title=Political Geography|url=http://site.ebrary.com.ezproxy.library.yorku.ca/lib/oculyork/reader.action?docID=10870263}}&lt;/ref&gt; A [[political system]] is a framework which defines acceptable political methods within a given society. [[History of political thought]] can be traced back to early antiquity, with seminal works such as [[Plato]]'s ''[[Republic (Plato)|Republic]]'', [[Aristotle]]'s ''[[Politics (Aristotle)|Politics]]'' and the works of [[Confucius]].

Formal Politics refers to the operation of a constitutional system of government and publicly defined institutions and procedures.&lt;ref name=&quot;Political Geography&quot;/&gt; Political parties, public policy or discussions about war and foreign affairs would fall under the category of Formal Politics.&lt;ref name=&quot;Political Geography&quot;/&gt; Many people view formal politics as something outside of themselves, but that can still affect their daily lives.&lt;ref name=&quot;Political Geography&quot;/&gt;

Informal Politics is understood as forming alliances, exercising power and protecting and advancing particular ideas or goals. Generally, this includes anything affecting one's daily life, such as the way an office or household is managed, or how one person or group exercises influence over another.&lt;ref name=&quot;Political Geography&quot;/&gt; Informal Politics is typically understood as everyday politics, hence the idea that &quot;politics is everywhere&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Political Geography&quot;/&gt;

== Etymology ==
The word comes from the same [[Ancient Greek|Greek]] word from which the title of [[Aristotle]]'s book ''[[Politics (Aristotle)|Politics]]'' (Πολιτικά, ''Politika'') also derives; ''politika'' means &quot;affairs of the cities&quot;. The book title was rendered in [[Early Modern English]] in the mid-15th century as &quot;Polettiques&quot;&lt;!--[sic]--&gt;;&lt;ref&gt;''The Diets and Sayings of the Philosophers'' (Early English Text Society, Original Series [https://books.google.com/books?id=M7G0AAAAIAAJ&amp;q= No. 211], 1941; reprinted 1961), p. 154: &quot;the book of Etiques&lt;!--[sic]--&gt; and of Polettiques&lt;!--[sic]--&gt;&quot;.&lt;/ref&gt; it became &quot;politics&quot; in [[Modern English]]. The singular ''politic'' first attested in English 1430 and comes from [[Middle French]] ''politique'', in turn from [[Latin]] ''politicus'',&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/hopper/text?doc=Perseus%3Atext%3A1999.04.0059%3Aentry%3Dpoliticus |title=A Latin Dictionary |author= Charlton T. Lewis, Charles Short |publisher=Perseus Digital Library |accessdate=2016-02-19}}&lt;/ref&gt; which is the [[Latinisation of names|Latinization]] of the Greek πολιτικός (''politikos''), meaning amongst others &quot;of, for, or relating to citizens&quot;, &quot;civil&quot;, &quot;civic&quot;, &quot;belonging to the state&quot;,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/hopper/text?doc=Perseus%3Atext%3A1999.04.0057%3Aentry%3Dpolitiko%2Fs πολιτικός |author=Henry George Liddell, Robert Scott |title=A Greek-English Lexicon |publisher=Perseus Digital Library |accessdate=2016-02-19}}&lt;/ref&gt; in turn from πολίτης (''polites''), &quot;citizen&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/hopper/text?doc=Perseus%3Atext%3A1999.04.0057%3Aentry%3Dpoli%2Fths πολίτης |author=Henry George Liddell, Robert Scott |title=A Greek-English Lexicon |publisher=Perseus Digital Library |accessdate=2016-02-19}}&lt;/ref&gt; and that from πόλις (''[[polis]]''), &quot;city&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/hopper/text?doc=Perseus%3Atext%3A1999.04.0057%3Aentry%3Dpo%2Flis πόλις |author=Henry George Liddell, Robert Scott |title=A Greek-English Lexicon |publisher=Perseus Digital Library |accessdate=2016-02-19}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== History of state politics ==

The history of politics is reflected in the origin, development, and economics of the institutions of [[government]].

=== The state ===
{{Main article|State (polity)}}

The origin of the [[State (polity)|state]] is to be found in the development of the [[Art of Warfare|art of warfare]]. Historically speaking, all political communities of the modern type owe their existence to successful warfare.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Carneiro|first=Robert L.|title=A Theory of the Origin of the State|journal=Science|date=21 August 1970|volume=169|issue=3947|doi=10.1126/science.169.3947.733|pmid=17820299|pages=733–8|bibcode=1970Sci...169..733C}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Kings, emperors and other types of monarchs in many countries including China and Japan, were considered divine. Of the institutions that ruled states, that of [[kingship]] stood at the forefront until the French Revolution put an end to the &quot;[[divine right of kings]]&quot;.  Nevertheless, the monarchy is among the longest-lasting political institutions, dating as early as 2100 BC in Sumeria&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Sumerian King List|url=http://gizidda.altervista.org/ebooks/Sumerian-King-List-chronology.pdf|accessdate=7 April 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;  to the 21st century AD British Monarchy.  Kingship becomes an institution through heredity.

The king often, even in [[Monarchy|absolute monarchies]], ruled his kingdom with the aid of an elite group of advisors, a [[Privy council|council]] without which he could not maintain power. As these advisors and others outside the monarchy negotiated for power, [[constitutional monarchy|constitutional monarchies]] emerged, which may be considered the germ of [[constitutional government]].{{Citation needed|date=January 2011}} Long before the council became a bulwark of democracy, it rendered invaluable aid to the institution of kingship by:{{Citation needed|date=January 2011}}

# Preserving the institution of kingship through heredity.
# Preserving the traditions of the social order.
# Being able to withstand criticism as an impersonal authority.
# Being able to manage a greater deal of knowledge and action than a single individual such as the king.

The greatest of the king's subordinates, the [[earls]] and [[dukes]] in England and Scotland, the [[dukes]] and [[counts]] in the Continent, always sat as a right on the council. A conqueror wages war upon the vanquished for vengeance or for plunder but an established kingdom exacts [[tribute]]. One of the functions of the council is to keep the coffers of the king full. Another is the satisfaction of [[military service]] and the establishment of [[lordship]]s by the king to satisfy the task of collecting taxes and soldiers.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Jenks |first=Edward |title=A history of politics |pages=73–96 |quote=The origin of the State, or Political Society, is to be found in the development of the art of military warfare.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==== The state and property ====

[[Property]] is the right vested on the individual or a group of people to enjoy the benefits of an object, be it material or intellectual. A right is a power enforced by public trust. Sometimes it happens that the exercise of a right is opposed to public trust. Nevertheless, a right is really an institution brought around by public trust, past, present or future. The growth of knowledge is the key to the history of property as an institution. The more man becomes knowledgeable of an object, be it physical or intellectual, the more it is appropriated. The appearance of the State brought about the final stage in the evolution of property from wildlife to husbandry. In the presence of the State, man can hold landed property. The State began granting lordships and ended up conferring property and with it came [[inheritance]]. With landed property came rent and in the exchange of goods, profit, so that in modern times, the &quot;lord of the land&quot; of long ago becomes the landlord. If it is, wrongly, assumed that the value of land is always the same, then there is no evolution of property whatsoever. However, the price of land goes up with every increase in something benefiting the landlord. The landlordism of large land owners has been the most rewarded of all political services. In industry, the position of the landlord is less important but in towns which have grown out of an industry, the fortunate landlord has reaped an enormous profit. Towards the latter part of the Middle Ages in Europe, both the State - the State would use the instrument of  [[confiscation]] for the first time to satisfy a debt - and the Church - the Church succeeded in acquiring immense quantities of land - were allied against the village community to displace the small landlord and they were successful to the extent that today, the village has become the ideal of the [[individualist]], a place in which every man &quot;does what he wills with his own.&quot; The State has been the most important factor in the evolution of the institution of property be it public or private.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Jenks |first=Edward |title=A history of politics |pages=97–111 |quote=No political institution is of greater importance, none has been the subject of greater controversy, than the institution of property.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==== The state and the justice system ====

As a primarily military institution, the State is concerned with the [[allegiance]] of its subjects, viewing disloyalty and [[espionage]] as well as other sorts of [[Conspiracy (political)|conspiracies]] as detrimental to its national security. Thus arises the law of [[treason]]. Criminal acts in general, breaking the peace and treason make up the whole, or at least part of [[criminal law]] enforced by the State as distinguished from [[Private law|the law enforced by private individuals or by the state on behalf of private individuals]]. State justice has taken the place of clan, feudal, merchant and ecclesiastical justice due to its strength, skill and simplicity. One very striking evidence of the superiority of the royal courts over the feudal and popular courts in the matter of official skill is the fact that, until comparatively late in history, the royal courts alone kept written records of their proceedings. The [[trial by jury]] was adopted by the Royal Courts, securing its popularity and making it a bulwark of liberty. By the time of the [[Protestant Reformation]], with the separation of Church and State, in the most progressive countries, the State succeeded in dealing with the business of administering justice.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Jenks |first=Edward |title=A history of politics |pages=112–124 |quote=We are so accustomed to look upon the administration of justice as an inevitable duty of the State...}}&lt;/ref&gt; Federalism shared power among states and federal government constituting a balance of powers between the Legislative, Executive, and Judicial branches.

==== The state and legislation ====

The making of laws was unknown to primitive societies.

That most persistent of all patriarchal societies, the [[Jewish]], retains to a certain extent its tribal law in the [[Gentile]] cities of the West. This tribal law is the rudimentary idea of law as it presented itself to people in the patriarchal stage of society; it was [[convention (norm)|custom]] or [[observance]] sanctioned by the approval and practice of ancestors.{{Citation needed|date=January 2011}}

The state of affairs which existed in the 10th century, when every town had its own laws and nations like France, Germany, Spain and other countries had no national law until the end of the 18th century, was brought to an end by three great agencies that helped to create the modern system of law and legislation:{{Citation needed|date=January 2011}}

# '''Records:''' From the early Middle Ages in Europe there come what are called folk-laws and they appear exactly at the time when the patriarchal was becoming the State. They are due almost universally to one cause: the desire of the king to know the custom of his subjects. These are not legislation in the sense of law-making but statements or declarations of custom. They are drawn from a knowledge of the custom of the people. Unwritten custom changes imperceptibly but not the written. It is always possible to point to the exact text and show what it says. Nevertheless, the written text can change by addition with every new edition.
# '''Law Courts:''' By taking some general rule which seemed to be common to all the communities and ignoring the differences, English common law was modeled after such a practice so that the law became common in all the districts of the kingdom. The reason why in the rest of Europe, there was no common law till centuries later is because the State in those countries did not get hold of the administration of justice when England did. One of the shrewdest moves by which the English judges pushed their plan of making a common law was by limiting the verdict of the jury in every case to [[questions of fact]]. At first the jury used to give answers both on law and fact; and being a purely local body, they followed local custom. A famous division came to pass: the province of the judge and the province of the jury.
# '''Fictions:''' Records and Law Courts were valuable in helping the people adapt to law-making but like Fictions, they were slow and imperfect. Though slowly, Fictions work because it is a well-known fact that people will accept a change in the form of a fiction while they would resist it to the end if the fact is out in the open.

Finally there is the enactment of laws or legislation. When progress and development is rapid, the faster method of [[political representation]] is adopted. This method does not originate in primitive society but in the State's need for money and its use of an assembly to raise the same. From the town assembly, a national assembly and the progress of commerce sprang [[parliament]]s all over Europe around the end of the 12th century, but not entirely representative or homogeneous for the nobility and the clergy. The clergy had amassed a fortune in land, about one-fifth of all Christendom but at the time, in the 12th and 13th centuries, the Church was following a policy of isolation; they adopted the rule of [[celibacy]] and cut themselves from domestic life; they refused to plead in a secular court; they refused to pay taxes to the State on the grounds that they had already paid it to the [[Pope]]. Since the main object of the king in holding a national assembly was to collect money, the Church could not be left out and so they came to Parliament. The Church did not like it but in most cases they had to come.{{Citation needed|date=January 2011}}

The medieval Parliament was complete when it represented all the states in the realm: nobles, clergy, peasants and craftsmen but it was not a popular institution mainly because it meant [[taxation]]. Only by the strongest pressure of the Crown were Parliaments maintained during the first century of their existence and the best proof of this assertion lies in the fact that in those countries where the Crown was weak, Parliament ceased to exist. The notion that parliaments were the result of a democratic movement cannot be supported by historical facts. Originally, the representative side of Parliament was solely concerned with money; representation in Parliament was a liability rather than a privilege. It is not uncommon that an institution created for one purpose begins to serve another. People who were asked to contribute with large sums of money began to [[petition]]. Pretty soon, sessions in Parliament would turn into bargaining tables, the king granting petitions in exchange for money. However, there were two kinds of petitions, one private and the other public and it was from this last that laws were adopted or [[legislation]] originated. The king as head of State could give orders to preserve territorial integrity but not until these royal enactments were combined with public petition that successful legislation ever took place. Even to the present day, this has always been the basis of all successful legislation: public custom is adopted and enforced by the State.{{Citation needed|date=January 2011}}

In the early days of political representation, the [[majority]] did not necessarily carry the day and there was very little need for contested [[election]]s but by the beginning of the 15th century, a seat in Parliament was something to be cherished. Historically speaking, the dogma of the equality of man is the result of the adoption of the purely practical machinery of the majority, but the adoption of the majority principle is also responsible for another institution of modern times: the [[party system]]. The party system is an elaborate piece of machinery that pits at least two political candidates against each other for the vote of an electorate; its advantage being equal representation interesting a large number of people in politics; it provides effective criticism of the government in power and it affords an outlet for the ambition of a large number of wealthy and educated people guaranteeing a consistent policy in a state.{{Citation needed|date=January 2011}}

These three institutions: political representation, majority rule and the party system are the basic components of modern political machinery; they are applicable to both central and local governments and are becoming by their adaptability ends in themselves rather than machinery to achieve some purpose.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Jenks |first=Edward |title=A history of politics |pages=124–139 |quote=As we have before stated (p. 41), the notion that law could be made was unknown to primitive society.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==== The state and the executive system ====

The administration is one of the most difficult aspects of government. In the enactment and enforcement of laws, the victory of the State is complete but not so in regards to administration – the reason being that it is easy to see the advantage of the enactment and enforcement of laws but not the administration of domestic, religious and business affairs which should be kept to a minimum by government.{{Citation needed|date=January 2011}}

Originally, the state was a military institution. For many years, it was just a territory ruled by a king who was surrounded by a small elite group of warriors and court officials and it was basically rule by force over a larger mass of people. Slowly, however, the people gained political representation for none can really be said to be a member of the State without the right of having a voice in the direction of policy making. One of the basic functions of the State in regards to administration is maintaining peace and internal order; it has no other excuse for interfering in the lives of its citizens. To maintain law and order the State develops means of [[communication]]. Historically, the &quot;king's highway&quot; was laid down and maintained for the convenience of the royal armies not as an incentive to [[commerce]]. In almost all countries, the State maintains the control of the means of communication and special freedoms such as those delineated in the [[First Amendment to the United States Constitution]] are rather limited. The State's original function of maintaining law and order within its borders gave rise to [[police]] administration which is a branch of the dispensation of [[Justice]] but on its preventive side, police jurisdiction has a special character of its own, which distinguishes it from ordinary judicial work. In the [[curfew]], the State shows early in history the importance of preventing disorder. In early days, next to maintaining law and order, the State was concerned with the raising of [[revenue]]. It was then useful to the State to establish a [[Technical standard|standard]] of [[weights and measures]] so that value could be generally accepted and finally the State acquired a [[monopoly]] of [[coin]]age. The regulation of labor by the State as one of its functions dates from the 15th century, when [[the Black Plague]] killed around half of the European population.{{Citation needed|date=January 2011}}

The invariable policy of the State has always been to break down all intermediate authorities and to deal directly with the individual. This was the policy until [[Adam Smith]]'s ''[[The Wealth of Nations]]'' was published promoting a strong public reaction against State interference. By its own action, the State raised the issue of the poor or the State relief of the [[indigent]]. The State, of course, did not create poverty but by destroying the chief agencies which dealt with it such as the village, the church and the [[guild]]s, it practically assumed full responsibility for the poor without exercising any power over it. The Great Poor Law Report of 1834 showed that [[communism]] was widespread in the rural areas of England. In newly developed countries such as the [[colonies]] of the [[British Empire]], the State has refused to take responsibility for the poor and the relief of poverty, although the poor classes lean heavily towards State socialism.{{Citation needed|date=January 2011}}

Taking into account the arguably significant powers of the State, it is only natural that in times of great crisis such as an overwhelming calamity the people should invoke general State aid.{{Citation needed|date=January 2011}}

Political representation has helped to shape State administration. When the voice of the individual can be heard, the danger of arbitrary interference by the State is greatly reduced. To that extent is the increase of State activity popular. There are no hard and fast rules to limit State administration but it is a fallacy to believe that the State is the nation and what the State does is necessarily for the good of the nation. In the first place, even in modern times, the State and the nation are never identical. Even where &quot;universal suffrage&quot; prevails, the fact remains that an extension of State administration means an increased interference of some by others, limiting freedom of action. Even if it is admitted that State and nation are one and the same, it is sometimes difficult to admit that State administration is necessarily good. Finally, the modern indiscriminate advocacy of State administration conceals the fallacy that State officials must necessarily prove more effective in their action than [[private enterprise]]. Herein lies the basic difference between [[Public administration|public]] and [[business administration]]; the first deals with the [[Common good|public weal]] while the second deals basically in [[Profit (accounting)|profit]], but both require a great deal of [[education]] and [[ethical code|ethical conduct]] to avoid the mishaps inherent in the relationship not only relating to [[Corporate law|business]] and [[labour rights|labour]] but also the State and the people administrating its [[government]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Jenks |first=Edward |title=A history of politics |pages=140–150 |quote=We come now to the last, and by far the most difficult department of State activity.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Themes ==

=== Forms of political organization ===
There are many forms of political organization, including states, non-government organizations (NGOs) and international organizations such as the [[United Nations]]. States are perhaps the predominant institutional form of political governance, where a state is understood as an institution and a government is understood as the [[regime]] in power.

According to Aristotle, states are classified into [[monarchies]], [[aristocracy|aristocracies]], [[Timocracy|timocracies]], [[democracies]], [[oligarchies]], and [[tyrannies]]. Due to changes across the history of politics, this classification has been abandoned. Generally speaking, no form of government could be considered the absolute best, as it would have to be the perfect form under all circumstances, for all people and in all ways. As an institution created by human nature to [[Governance|govern society]], it is vulnerable to [[political corruption|abuse by people for their own gain]], no matter what form of government a state utilizes, thus suggesting there is no 'best' form of government.

All states are varieties of a single organizational form, the sovereign state. All the [[great powers]] of the modern world rule on the principle of [[sovereignty]]. Sovereign power may be vested on an individual as in an [[autocracy|autocratic government]] or it may be vested on a group as in a constitutional government. [[Constitutions]] are written documents that specify and limit the powers of the different branches of government. Although a constitution is a written document, there is also an unwritten constitution. The unwritten constitution is continually being written by the legislative branch of government; this is just one of those cases in which the nature of the circumstances determines the form of government that is most appropriate. England did set the fashion of written constitutions during the [[English Civil War|Civil War]] but after the [[Restoration (England)|Restoration]] abandoned them to be taken up later by the [[American Colonies]] after their [[American Revolution|emancipation]] and then [[France]] after the [[French Revolution|Revolution]] and the rest of Europe including the European colonies.{{Citation needed|date=January 2011}}

There are many forms of government. One form is a strong central government as in France and China. Another form is local government, such as the ancient divisions in England that are comparatively weaker but less bureaucratic. These two forms helped to shape the practice of [[federal government]], first in Switzerland, then in the United States in 1776, in Canada in 1867 and in Germany in 1871 and in 1901, [[Australia]]. Federal states introduced the new principle of agreement or [[contract]]. Compared to a [[federation]], a [[confederation]] has a more dispersed system of [[judicial power]].{{Citation needed|date=April 2010}} In the [[American Civil War]], the contention of the Confederate States that a State could [[secede]] from the Union was untenable because of the power enjoyed by the Federal government in the executive, legislative and judiciary branches.{{Citation needed|date=January 2011}}

According to professor [[A. V. Dicey]] in ''An Introduction to the Study of the Law of the Constitution'', the essential features of a federal constitution are: a) A written supreme constitution in order to prevent disputes between the jurisdictions of the Federal and State authorities; b) A distribution of power between the Federal and State governments and c) A Supreme Court vested with the power to interpret the Constitution and enforce the law of the land remaining independent of both the executive and legislative branches.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Jenks |first=Edward |title=A history of politics |url=https://books.google.com/?id=Z3gCAAAAYAAJ&amp;pg=PA1&amp;dq=politics+history#v=onepage&amp;q= |pages=1–164 |year=1900 |publisher=J. M. Dent &amp; Co. |accessdate=2016-02-19}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Global politics ===
{{Main article| Global politics}}
'''[[Global politics]]''' include different '''practices''' of political [[globalization]] in relation to questions of social power: from global patterns of governance to issues of globalizing conflict. The 20th century witnessed the outcome of two world wars and not only the rise and fall of the [[Third Reich]] but also the rise and fall of [[communism]]. The development of the [[atomic bomb]] gave the United States a more rapid end to its conflict in Japan in [[World War II]]. Later, the development of the [[hydrogen bomb]] became the ultimate weapon of mass destruction.

Global politics also concerns the rise of global and international '''organizations'''. The [[United Nations]] has served as a forum for peace in a world threatened by nuclear war, &quot;The invention of nuclear and space weapons has made war unacceptable as an instrument for achieving political ends.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Rabinowitch |first=Eugene |authorlink=Eugene Rabinowitch |title=Bulletin of the Atomic Scientists |url=https://books.google.com/?id=-QsAAAAAMBAJ&amp;pg=PA13&amp;dq=World+politics+final+nuclear+holocaust&amp;q=World%20politics%20final%20nuclear%20holocaust |date=June 1973 |page=13 |issn=0096-3402 |quote=...the rationale of traditional patterns of world politics. |publisher=Educational Foundation for Nuclear Science, Inc.}}&lt;/ref&gt; Although an all-out final nuclear holocaust is out of the question for man, &quot;[[nuclear blackmail]]&quot; comes into question not only on the issue of world peace but also on the issue of national sovereignty.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Dulles |first=Allen |authorlink=Allen Dulles |title=The Craft of Intelligence |url=https://books.google.com/?id=mH3qdHK6_EsC&amp;pg=PA224&amp;dq=the+craft+of+intelligence+April+1963#v=onepage&amp;q= |page=224 |year=2006 |publisher=Globe Pequot |isbn=1599215772 |quote=...using 'nuclear blackmail' as a threat to intimidate other countries.}}&lt;/ref&gt; On a Sunday in 1962, the world stood still at the brink of nuclear war during the October [[Cuban Missile Crisis]] from the implementation of U.S. vs [[U.S.S.R.]] nuclear blackmail policy.

According to [[political science]] professor [[Paul James (academic)|Paul James]], global politics is affected by ''values'': norms of [[human rights]], ideas of [[human development (humanity)|human development]], and beliefs such as [[cosmopolitanism]] about how we should relate to each:
{{quote| Cosmopolitanism can be defined as a global politics that, firstly, projects a sociality of common political engagement among all human beings across the globe, and, secondly, suggests that this sociality should be either ethically or organizationally privileged over other forms of sociality.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book | year= 2014 | last1= James | first1= Paul | authorlink= Paul James (academic) | title= Globalization and Politics, Vol. 4: Political Philosophies of the Global | url= http://www.academia.edu/7547819/Globalization_and_Politics_Vol._4_Political_Philosophies_of_the_Global_2014_ | publisher= Sage Publications | location= London | pages= x | accessdate= 2016-02-19}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

=== Political corruption ===
{{Main article|Political corruption}}
[[William Pitt the Elder]], speaking before the British [[House of Lords]], 9 January 1770, observed: &quot;Unlimited power is apt to corrupt the minds of those who possess it.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=Safire's Political Dictionary |editor-first=William|editor-last=Safire |date=2008 |publisher=Oxford University Press |page=566}}&lt;/ref&gt; This was echoed more famously by [[John Dalberg-Acton]] over a century later: &quot;Power tends to corrupt, and absolute power corrupts absolutely.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;lmcone&quot;&gt;Dalberg-Acton, John (Lord Acton). [http://history.hanover.edu/courses/excerpts/165acton.html Letter to Bishop Mandell Creighton, April 5, 1887]. Published in ''Historical Essays and Studies'', edited by J. N. Figgis and R. V. Laurence (London: Macmillan, 1907)&lt;/ref&gt;

'''Political corruption''' is the use of legislated powers by government officials for illegitimate private gain. Misuse of government power for other purposes, such as [[Political repression|repression]] of political opponents and general [[police brutality]], is not considered political corruption. Neither are illegal acts by private persons or corporations not directly involved with the government. An illegal act by an officeholder constitutes political corruption only if the act is directly related to their official duties and/or power.{{Citation needed|date=January 2011}}

Forms of corruption vary, but include [[corruption]], [[extortion]], [[cronyism]], [[nepotism]], [[patronage]], [[Graft (politics)|graft]], and [[embezzlement]]. While corruption may facilitate [[Organized crime|criminal enterprise]] such as [[drug trafficking]], [[money laundering]], and [[human trafficking|trafficking]], it is not restricted to these activities. {{Citation needed|date=January 2011}} The activities that constitute illegal corruption differ depending on the country or jurisdiction. For instance, certain political funding practices that are legal in one place may be illegal in another. In some cases, government officials have broad or poorly defined powers, which make it difficult to distinguish between legal and illegal actions.{{Citation needed|date=January 2011}} Worldwide, bribery alone is estimated to involve over 1 trillion US dollars annually.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/business/6288400.stm|title=BBC NEWS - Business - African corruption 'on the wane'|publisher=}}&lt;/ref&gt; A state of unrestrained political corruption is known as a [[kleptocracy]], literally meaning &quot;rule by thieves&quot;.{{Citation needed|date=January 2011}}

=== Political parties ===
{{Main article|political party}}

A '''political party''' is a [[political organization]] that typically seeks to attain and maintain political power within [[government]], usually by participating in [[elections|electoral campaigns]], educational outreach or protest actions. Parties often espouse an expressed [[ideology]] or vision bolstered by a written [[Party platform|platform]] with specific goals, forming a [[coalition]] among disparate interests.{{Citation needed|date=January 2011}}

=== Politics as an academic discipline ===

[[Political science]], the study of politics, examines the acquisition and application of [[political power|power]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Safire |first=William |title=Safire's Political Dictionary |url=https://books.google.com/?id=jK-0NPoMiYoC&amp;pg=PA566&amp;dq=power+corrupts+and+absolute+power+corrupts+absolutely#v=onepage&amp;q=power%20corrupts%20and%20absolute%20power%20corrupts%20absolutely |page=566 |year=2008 |publisher=Oxford University Press US |isbn=0-19-534334-4 |quote=Power tends to corrupt; absolute power corrupts absolutely.}}&lt;/ref&gt; Political scientist [[Harold Lasswell]] defined politics as &quot;who gets what, when, and how&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Schmidt|first=Barbara A.|last2=Bardes|first2=Mack C.|last3=Shelley|first3=Steffen W.|title=American Government and Politics Today: The Essentials|year=2011|publisher=Wadsworth, Cengage Learning|location=Boston|isbn=978-0-538-49719-0|edition=2011–2012 Student|page=5}}&lt;/ref&gt; Related areas of study include [[political philosophy]], which seeks a rationale for politics and an ethic of public behaviour, [[political economy]], which attempts to develop understandings of the relationships between politics and the economy and the governance of the two, and [[public administration]], which examines the practices of governance.{{Citation needed|date=January 2011}} The philosopher [[Charles Blattberg]], who has defined politics as &quot;responding to conflict with dialogue,&quot; offers an account which distinguishes political philosophies from political ideologies.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last=Blattberg |first=Charles |title=Political Philosophies and Political Ideologies |journal=Public Affairs Quarterly |date=July 2001 |volume=15 |issue=3 |pages=193–217 |url=http://ssrn.com/abstract=1755117 |accessdate=26 April 2013 |issn=0887-0373}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The first academic chair devoted to politics in the United States was the chair of history and political science at [[Columbia University]], first occupied by Prussian émigré [[Francis Lieber]] in 1857.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last1=Farr |first1=James |last2=Seidelman |first2=Raymond |title=Discipline and history |url=https://books.google.com/?id=e9_jbbroRHsC&amp;pg=PA70&amp;dq=Discipline+and+history+Francis+Lieber+Karl+Marx&amp;q= |year=1993 |publisher=University of Michigan Press |isbn=0-472-06512-2 |quote=...a chair at Columbia in 1857 as professor of history and political science, the very first of its kind in America.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Political values ==
[[File:Inglehart Values Map.svg|thumb|300px|Political views differ on average across nations. A recreation of the [[Ronald Inglehart|Inglehart]]–[[Christian Welzel|Welzel]] Cultural Map of the World based on the [[World Values Survey]].]]
{{Main article|Political spectrum}}

Several different [[political spectrum]]s have been proposed.

=== Left–right politics ===
Political analysts and politicians divide politics into [[left wing]] and [[right wing]] politics, often also using the idea of center politics as a middle path of policy between the right and left. This classification is comparatively recent (it was not used by [[Aristotle]] or [[Hobbes]], for instance), and dates from the [[French Revolution]] era, when those members of the [[National Assembly]] who supported the [[republic]], the common people and a [[secular society]] sat on the left and supporters of the [[monarchy]], [[aristocracy (class)|aristocratic]] privilege and the Church sat on the right.&lt;ref name=&quot;Knapp&quot;&gt;{{cite book|author=Andrew Knapp and Vincent Wright|title=The Government and Politics of France|year=2006|publisher=Routledge}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The meanings behind the labels have become more complicated over the years. A particularly influential event was the publication of the [[Communist Manifesto]] by [[Karl Marx]] and [[Frederick Engels]] in 1848. The ''Manifesto'' suggested a course of action for a [[proletarian]] revolution to overthrow the [[bourgeoisie|bourgeois]] society and abolish private property, in the belief that this would lead to a [[classless]] and [[Stateless communism|stateless]] society.{{Citation needed|date=January 2011}}

The meaning of left-wing and right-wing varies considerably between different countries and at different times, but generally speaking, it can be said that the right wing often values [[tradition]] and [[social stratification]] while the left wing often values [[reform]] and [[egalitarianism]], with the center seeking a balance between the two such as with [[social democracy]] or [[Regulated market|regulated capitalism]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.encyclopedia.com/doc/1G2-3045000932.html#C |author=Daniel J. Levinson |title=CONSERVATISM AND RADICALISM |publisher=''International Encyclopedia of the Social Sciences'' |accessdate=2016-02-19}}&lt;/ref&gt;

According to [[Norberto Bobbio]], one of the major exponents of this distinction, the Left believes in attempting to eradicate social inequality, while the Right regards most social inequality as the result of ineradicable natural inequalities, and sees attempts to enforce social equality as utopian or authoritarian.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bobbio&quot;&gt;[[Norberto Bobbio|Bobbio]], Norberto, ''Left and Right: The Significance of a Political Distinction'' (translated by Allan Cameron), 1997, [[University of Chicago Press]]. ISBN 0-226-06246-5&lt;/ref&gt;

Some ideologies, notably [[Christian Democracy]], claim to combine left and right wing politics; according to Geoffrey K. Roberts and Patricia Hogwood, &quot;In terms of ideology, Christian Democracy has incorporated many of the views held by liberals, conservatives and socialists within a wider framework of moral and Christian principles.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Roberts and Hogwood, ''European Politics Today'', [[Manchester University Press]], 1997&lt;/ref&gt; Movements which claim or formerly claimed to be above the left-right divide include [[Fascist]] [[Terza Posizione]] economic politics in Italy, [[Gaullism]] in France, [[Peronism]] in Argentina, and [[National Action Party (Mexico)#&quot;National Action&quot; politics|National Action Party]] in Mexico.{{Citation needed|date=January 2011}}

=== Authoritarian–libertarian politics ===

[[Authoritarianism]] and [[civil libertarianism|libertarianism]] refer to the amount of individual [[Freedom (political)|freedom]] each person possesses in that society relative to the state. One author describes authoritarian political systems as those where &quot;individual [[rights]] and goals are subjugated to group goals, expectations and conformities&quot;,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|author=Markus Kemmelmeier|title=Individualism, Collectivism, and Authoritarianism in Seven Societies|year=2003|journal=Journal of Cross-Cultural Psychology|volume=34|issue=3|pages=304–322|doi=10.1177/0022022103034003005|display-authors=1|last2=Burnstein|first2=Eugene|last3=Krumov|first3=Krum|last4=Genkova|first4=Petia|last5=Kanagawa|first5=Chie|last6=Hirshberg|first6=Matthew S.|last7=Erb|first7=Hans-Peter|last8=Wieczorkowska|first8=Grazyna|last9=Noels|first9=Kimberly A.}}&lt;/ref&gt; while libertarians generally oppose the [[Sovereign state|state]] and hold the [[individual]] as [[sovereign]]. In their purest form, libertarians are [[anarchism|anarchists]], who argue for the total abolition of the state, of [[political parties]] and of [[Political organisation|other political entities]], while the purest authoritarians are, theoretically, [[totalitarianism|totalitarians]] who support state control over all aspects of [[society]].{{Citation needed|date=January 2011}}

For instance, [[classical liberalism]] (also known as ''[[laissez-faire]] liberalism'',&lt;ref name=Adams&gt;Ian Adams, ''Political Ideology Today'' (Manchester: Manchester University Press, 2001), 20.&lt;/ref&gt; ) is a doctrine stressing individual freedom and [[limited government]]. This includes the importance of human rationality, individual [[property rights]], [[free market]]s, [[natural rights]], the protection of [[civil liberties]], constitutional limitation of government, and individual freedom from restraint as exemplified in the writings of [[John Locke]], [[Adam Smith]], [[David Hume]], [[David Ricardo]], [[Voltaire]], [[Montesquieu]] and others. According to the libertarian [[Institute for Humane Studies]], &quot;the libertarian, or 'classical liberal,' perspective is that individual well-being, prosperity, and social harmony are fostered by 'as much liberty as possible' and 'as little government as necessary.'&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.theihs.org/about/id.1084/default.asp What Is Libertarian?], Institute for Humane Studies {{wayback|url=http://www.theihs.org/about/id.1084/default.asp |date=20070324231417 |df=y }}&lt;/ref&gt;
For anarchist political philosopher [[L. Susan Brown]] &quot;Liberalism and [[anarchism]] are two political philosophies that are fundamentally concerned with individual [[Freedom of will|freedom]] yet differ from one another in very distinct ways. Anarchism shares with liberalism a radical commitment to individual freedom while rejecting liberalism's competitive property relations.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceA&quot;&gt;[[L. Susan Brown]]. ''[[The Politics of Individualism: Liberalism, Liberal Feminism, and Anarchism]]''. BLACK ROSE BOOKS LID. 1993&lt;/ref&gt;

== See also ==
{{Portal|Politics}}
{{Wikipedia books}}
* [[Index of law articles]]
* [[Index of politics articles]] - alphabetical list of political subjects
* [[List of years in politics]]
* [[Outline of law]]
* [[Outline of political science]] - structured list of political topics, arranged by subject area
* [[Political lists]] - lists of political topics
* [[Politics of present-day states]]
* [[Political organisation]]
* [[List of political ideologies]]

== Notes ==
{{reflist|2}}

== References ==
* {{Cite book | year= 1981 | last1= Connolly | first1=William | authorlink=William E. Connolly | title=Appearance and Reality in Politics | publisher= Cambridge University Press | location= Cambridge}}
* {{Cite book | year= 2014 | last1= James | first1= Paul | authorlink= Paul James (academic) | last2= Soguk | first2= Nevzat | title= Globalization and Politics, Vol. 1: Global Political and Legal Governance | url= http://www.academia.edu/7285675/Globalization_and_Politics_Vol._1_Global_Political_and_Legal_Governance_2014_| publisher= Sage Publications | location= London | accessdate= 2016-02-19}}
* Ryan, Alan: ''On Politics: A History of Political Thought from Herodotus to the Present.'' London: Allen Lane, 2012. ISBN 978-0-713-99364-6

== External links ==
{{Sister project links|Politics}}

{{Ideologies}}
{{Humanities}}

{{Use dmy dates|date=May 2011}}

{{Authority control}}

[[Category:Politics| ]]</text>
      <sha1>mwhq3tk13lc6bic7yhhcndz6yd3nvzu</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Java</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>69336</id>
    <revision>
      <id>736312803</id>
      <parentid>736309007</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-08-26T16:36:16Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Gunkarta</username>
        <id>2322177</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Reverted 2 edits by [[Special:Contributions/Shubham4154|Shubham4154]] ([[User talk:Shubham4154|talk]]) to last revision by GarudaPhoenix. ([[WP:TW|TW]])</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="48727">{{about|the Indonesian island|the programming language|Java (programming language)|other uses|Java (disambiguation)}}
{{Infobox islands
|name = Java &lt;br&gt; ''Jawa ([[Indonesian language|Indonesian]])'' &lt;br&gt; ''ꦗꦮ ([[Javanese language|Javanese]])'' &lt;br&gt; ''ᮏᮝ ([[Sundanese language|Sundanese]])''
|image name = Java Topography.png
|image caption = Topography of Java
|locator map = Java_Locator.svg
|location = [[Southeast Asia]]
|coordinates = {{Coord|7|29|30|S|110|00|16|E|type:isle_region:ID_scale:5000000|display=inline,title}}
|archipelago = [[Greater Sunda Islands]]
|area km2 = 128297
|rank = 13th
|highest mount = [[Semeru]]
|elevation m = 3676
|country = [[Indonesia|Republic of Indonesia]]
|country admin divisions title = Provinces
|country admin divisions = [[Banten]],&lt;br /&gt;[[Jakarta|Special&amp;nbsp;Capital&amp;nbsp;Region&amp;nbsp;of&amp;nbsp;Jakarta]],&lt;br /&gt;[[West Java]],&lt;br /&gt;[[Central Java]],&lt;br /&gt;[[East Java]],&lt;br /&gt;[[Yogyakarta|Yogyakarta Special Region]]
|country largest city = [[Jakarta]]
|country largest city area = 661.52&amp;nbsp;km²
|population = 145 million
|population as of = 2015
|density km2 = 1121
|ethnic groups = [[Javanese people|Javanese]] (inc. [[Tenggerese]], [[Osing people|Osing]], [[Banyumasan people|Banyumasan]], [[Cirebonese]]), [[Sundanese people|Sundanese]] (inc. [[Bantenese]], [[Baduy]]), [[Betawi people|Betawi]], [[Madurese people|Madurese]]
}}

'''Java''' ([[Indonesian language|Indonesian]]: '''''Jawa'''''; [[Javanese language|Javanese]]: '''''ꦗꦮ'''''; [[Sundanese language|Sundanese]]: '''''ᮏᮝ''''') is an [[island]] of [[Indonesia]].  With a population of over 141 million (the island itself) or 145 million (the administrative region) {{As of|2015|lc=y}} Census released in December 2015,&lt;ref name=&quot;citypopulation.de&quot;&gt;[http://citypopulation.de/Indonesia-MU.html Indonesia: Urban Population of Cities] Retrieved 22 December 2015.&lt;/ref&gt; Java is home to 56.7 percent of the [[Demographics of Indonesia|Indonesian population]] and is the [[List of islands by population|most populous island]] on [[Earth]]. The [[Indonesia]]n capital city, [[Jakarta]], is located on [[West Java|western Java]]. Much of Indonesian history took place on Java. It was the center of powerful Hindu-Buddhist empires, the Islamic sultanates, and the core of the colonial [[Dutch East Indies]]. Java was also the center of the [[History of Indonesia|Indonesian struggle for independence]] during the 1930s and 1940s. Java dominates [[Indonesia]] politically, economically and culturally.

Formed mostly as the result of volcanic eruptions, Java is the [[List of islands by area|13th largest island]] in the world and the [[List of islands of Indonesia|fifth largest]] in [[Indonesia]]. A chain of volcanic mountains forms an east–west spine along the island. Three main languages are spoken on the island: [[Javanese language|Javanese]], [[Sundanese language|Sundanese]], and [[Madurese language|Madurese]].  Of these, Javanese is the dominant; it is the native language of about 60 million people in Indonesia, most of whom live on Java. Furthermore, most residents are [[bilingual]], speaking Indonesian (the official language of Indonesia) as their first or second language. While the majority of the people of Java are Muslim, Java has a diverse mixture of religious beliefs, ethnicities, and cultures.

Java is divided into four provinces, [[West Java]], [[Central Java]], [[East Java]], and [[Banten]], and two special regions, [[Jakarta]] and [[Yogyakarta (special region)|Yogyakarta]].

==Etymology==
The origins of the name &quot;Java&quot; are not clear. One possibility is that the island was named after the [[Foxtail millet|''jáwa-wut'']] plant, which was said to be common in the island during the time, and that prior to Indianization the island had different names.&lt;ref&gt;Raffles, Thomas E.: ''[[The History of Java (1817 book)|History of Java]]''. Oxford University Press, 1965, p. 2.&lt;/ref&gt; There are other possible sources: the word ''jaú'' and its variations mean &quot;beyond&quot; or &quot;distant&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Raffles, Thomas E. 1965. Page 3&quot;&gt;Raffles, Thomas E.: ''[[The History of Java (1817 book)|History of Java]]''. Oxford University Press, 1965, p. 3.&lt;/ref&gt; And, in [[Sanskrit]] ''yava'' means barley, a plant for which the island was famous.&lt;ref name=&quot;Raffles, Thomas E. 1965. Page 3&quot;/&gt; &quot;Yawadvipa&quot; is mentioned in [[India]]'s earliest epic, the [[Ramayana]]. [[Sugriva]], the chief of [[Rama]]'s army dispatched his men to Yawadvipa, the island of Java, in search of [[Sita]].&lt;ref&gt;[https://books.google.com/books?id=9ic4BjWFmNIC&amp;pg=PA465 History of Ancient India Kapur, Kamlesh]&lt;/ref&gt; It was hence referred to in India by the Sanskrit name &quot;yāvaka dvīpa&quot; (dvīpa = island). Java is mentioned in the ancient Tamil text ''[[Manimekalai]]'' by [[Chithalai Chathanar]] that states that Java had a kingdom with a capital called Nagapuram.&lt;ref&gt;Hindu culture in ancient India by Sekharipuram Vaidyanatha Viswanatha, p. 177.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Tamil Literature by M. S. Purnalingam Pillai, p. 46.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;The Tamils Eighteen Hundred Years Ago by V. Kanakasabhai, p. 11.&lt;/ref&gt; Another source states that the &quot;Java&quot; word is derived from a [[Proto-Austronesian language|Proto-Austronesian]] root word, ''Iawa'' that meaning &quot;home&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Hatley, R., Schiller, J., Lucas, A., Martin-Schiller, B., (1984). &quot;Mapping cultural regions of Java&quot; in: Other Javas away from the kraton. pp. 1–32.&lt;/ref&gt; The great island of Iabadiu or Jabadiu was mentioned in [[Ptolemy|Ptolemy's]] ''[[Geography (Ptolemy)|Geographia]]'' composed around 150 CE [[Roman Empire]]. ''Iabadiu'' is said to means &quot;barley island&quot;, to be rich in gold, and have a silver town called Argyra at the west end. The name indicate Java,&lt;ref name =&quot;AncientGeo&quot;&gt;{{cite book|title=History of Ancient Geography|author=J. Oliver Thomson|publisher=[[Cambridge University Press]]|year=2013|isbn=9781107689923|url =https://books.google.co.id/books?id=GpP0wKQ1lksC&amp;printsec=frontcover#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false|pages=316–317}}&lt;/ref&gt; and seems to be derived from Hindu name Java-dvipa (Yawadvipa).

==Geography==
{{See also|Volcanoes of Java}}
[[File:Mount Bromo (2012).JPG|left|thumb|249x249px|[[Mount Bromo]] in [[East Java]]]]
Java lies between [[Sumatra]] to the west and [[Bali]] to the east. [[Borneo]] lies to the north and [[Christmas Island]] is to the south. It is the [[list of islands by area|world's 13th largest island]]. Java is surrounded by the [[Java Sea]] to the north, [[Sunda Strait]] to the west, the [[Indian Ocean]] to the south and [[Bali Strait]] and [[Madura Strait]] in the east.

Java is almost entirely of [[volcano|volcanic]] origin; it contains thirty-eight [[mountains]] forming an east–west spine that have at one time or another been active [[volcano]]es. The highest volcano in Java is Mount [[Semeru]] (3,676 m). The most active volcano in Java and also in Indonesia is [[Mount Merapi]] (2,930 m).

More mountains and highlands help to split the interior into a series of relatively isolated regions suitable for [[Paddy field|wet-rice]] cultivation; the rice lands of Java are among the richest in the world.&lt;ref name=&quot;RICKLEFS_p15&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=Ricklefs|first=M. C.|title=A History of Modern Indonesia since c.1300|edition=2|publisher=MacMillan|year=1990|location=London|page=15|isbn=0-333-57690-X}}&lt;/ref&gt; Java was the first place where [[Indonesian coffee]] was grown, starting in 1699. Today, [[Coffea arabica]] is grown on the Ijen Plateau by small-holders and larger plantations.
[[File:COLLECTIE TROPENMUSEUM De weg van Buitenzorg naar de Preanger Regentschappen TMnr 3728-429c.jpg|thumb|[[Parahyangan]] highland near [[Buitenzorg]], c. 1865–1872]]

The area of Java is approximately 150,000&amp;nbsp;km&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;ref name=&quot;MONK_7&quot;&gt;{{cite book |last=Monk, |first=K. A.|author2=Fretes, Y.|author3=Reksodiharjo-Lilley, G.|title=The Ecology of Nusa Tenggara and Maluku |publisher=Periplus Editions Ltd.|year=1996|page=7|location=Hong Kong|isbn=962-593-076-0}}&lt;/ref&gt; It is about {{convert|1000|km|abbr=on}} long and up to {{convert|210|km|abbr=on}} wide. The island's longest [[river]] is the 600&amp;nbsp;km long [[Solo River (Java)|Solo River]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.jasatirta1.go.id/english/3WorkArea/20BengawanSolo.htm Management of Bengawan Solo River Area] Jasa Tirta I Corporation 2004. Retrieved 26 July 2006.&lt;/ref&gt; The river rises from its source in central Java at the [[Mount Lawu|Lawu]] volcano, then flows north and eastward to its mouth in the [[Java Sea]] near the city of [[Surabaya]]. Other major rivers are [[Brantas]], [[Citarum]], [[Manuk River|Cimanuk]] and [[Serayu River|Serayu]].

The average temperature ranges from 22&amp;nbsp;°C to 29&amp;nbsp;°C; average humidity is 75%. The northern coastal plains are normally hotter, averaging 34&amp;nbsp;°C during the day in the [[dry season]]. The south coast is generally cooler than the north, and highland areas inland are even cooler.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Climate, Weather, and Temperature of Java Indonesia|url=http://www.javaindonesia.org/general/climate-weather-temperature-java-indonesia/|accessdate=1 April 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[wet season]] begins in November and ends in April. During that rain falls mostly in the afternoons and intermittently during other parts of the year. The wettest months are January and February.

West Java is wetter than East Java and mountainous regions receive much higher rainfall. The [[Parahyangan]] highlands of West Java receive over 4,000&amp;nbsp;mm annually, while the north coast of East Java receives 900&amp;nbsp;mm annually.

==Natural environment==
[[File:Tanjung Gelam - Karimunjawa.jpg|left|thumb|Tanjung Gelam, a beach in [[Karimunjawa National Park|Karimunjawa]]]]
The [[natural environment]] of Java is [[tropical rainforest]], with ecosystems ranging from coastal [[mangrove]] forests on the north coast, rocky coastal cliffs on the southern coast, and low-lying tropical forests to high altitude rainforests on the slopes of mountainous volcanic regions in the interior. The Javan environment and climate gradually alters from west to east; from wet and humid dense rainforest in western parts, to a dry [[savanna]] environment in the east, corresponding to the climate and rainfall in these regions.[[File:Java-1934 -2.jpg|thumb|Male [[Javan rhinoceros|Javan rhino]] shot in 1934 in West Java. Today only small numbers of Javan rhino survive in [[Ujung Kulon National Park|Ujung Kulon]]; it is the world's rarest rhino.]]Originally Javan wildlife supported a rich biodiversity, where numbers of [[endemic]] species of flora and fauna flourished; such as the [[Javan rhinoceros]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.edgeofexistence.org/mammals/species_info.php?id=11 |title=Javan Rhinoceros (Rhinoceros sondaicus) |author= |work= |publisher=EDGE Evolutionarily Distinct and Globally Endangered |accessdate=26 June 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Banteng|Javan banteng]], [[Javan warty pig]], [[Nisaetus bartelsi|Javan hawk-eagle]], [[Pavo muticus|Javan peafowl]], [[Silvery gibbon|Javan silvery gibbon]], [[Javan lutung]], [[Java mouse-deer]], [[Javan rusa]], and [[Javan leopard]]. With over 450 species of birds and 37 endemic species, Java is a birdwatcher's paradise.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://wildlifenews.co.uk/2011/indonesia-bird-watching-tour-with-wildlife-news-travel/ |title=Indonesia bird watching tour |author= |work= |publisher=wildlifenews.co.uk |accessdate=26 June 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; There are about 130 freshwater fish species in Java.&lt;ref&gt;Nguyen, T. T. T., and S. S. De Silva (2006). ''Freshwater finfish biodiversity and conservation: an asian perspective.'' Biodiversity &amp; Conservation 15(11): 3543-3568.&lt;/ref&gt;

Since ancient times, people have opened the rainforest, altered the ecosystem, shaped the landscapes and created [[rice paddy]] and terraces to support the growing population. Javan rice terraces have existed for more than a millennium, and had supported ancient agricultural kingdoms. The growing human population has put severe pressure on Java's wildlife, as rainforests were diminished and confined to highland slopes or isolated peninsulas. Some of Java's endemic species are now critically endangered, with some already extinct; Java used to have [[Javan tiger]]s and [[Javan elephant]]s, but both have been rendered extinct. Today, several national parks exist in Java that protect the remnants of its fragile wildlife, such as [[Ujung Kulon National Park|Ujung Kulon]], [[Mount Halimun Salak National Park|Mount Halimun-Salak]], [[Gunung Gede Pangrango National Park|Gede Pangrango]], [[Baluran National Park|Baluran]], [[Meru Betiri National Park|Meru Betiri]] and [[Alas Purwo National Park|Alas Purwo]].

==Administrative division==
The island as well as nearby islands are administratively jointly, divided into four [[Provinces of Indonesia|provinces]]:
*[[Banten]], capital: [[Serang]]
*[[West Java]], capital: [[Bandung]]
*[[Central Java]], capital: [[Semarang]]
*[[East Java]], capital: [[Surabaya]]
and two special regions:
*[[Jakarta]]
*[[Yogyakarta (special region)|Yogyakarta]]
and 4 cultural zones:
*Western Java (Banten, West Java, and Jakarta)
*Central Java (Central Java and Yogyakarta)
*East Java excluding Madura Island
* Madura Island

==History==
[[File:MerbabuSawah.jpg|thumb|left|[[Mount Merbabu]] surrounded by rice fields. Java's volcanic topography and rich agricultural lands are the fundamental factors in its history.]]

Fossilised remains of ''[[Homo erectus]]'', popularly known as the &quot;[[Java Man]]&quot;, dating back 1.7 million years were found along the banks of the [[Bengawan Solo River]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Pope|title=Recent advances in far eastern paleoanthropology |journal=Annual Review of Anthropology|volume=17|pages=43–77|year=1988|doi=10.1146/annurev.an.17.100188.000355|first1=G. G.}}
cited in {{cite book|last=Whitten|first=T.|author2=Soeriaatmadja, R. E.|author3=Suraya A. A.|title=The Ecology of Java and Bali|publisher=Periplus Editions Ltd|year=1996|location=Hong Kong|pages=309–312}}; {{cite journal|last=Pope|first=G.|title=Evidence on the Age of the Asian Hominidae|journal=Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America|volume=80|issue=16|pages=4,988–4992|date=15 August 1983|doi=10.1073/pnas.80.16.4988|pmid=6410399|pmc=384173}}
cited in
{{cite book|last=Whitten|first=T.|author2=Soeriaatmadja, R. E.|author3=Suraya A. A. |title=The Ecology of Java and Bali |publisher=Periplus Editions Ltd|year=1996|location=Hong Kong|page=309}};
{{cite journal|last=de Vos|first=J. P.|author2=P. Y. Sondaar|title=Dating hominid sites in Indonesia|journal=Science Magazine|volume=266|issue=16|pages=4,988–4992|date=9 December 1994 |url=http://www.sciencemag.org/cgi/reprint/266/5191/1726.pdf|format=PDF|doi=10.1126/science.7992059}}
cited in {{cite book|last=Whitten|first=T|author2=Soeriaatmadja, R. E.|author3=Suraya A. A.|title=The Ecology of Java and Bali|publisher=Periplus Editions Ltd|year=1996|location=Hong Kong|page=309}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The island's exceptional fertility and rainfall allowed the development of wet-field rice cultivation, which required sophisticated levels of cooperation between villages. Out of these village alliances, small kingdoms developed. The chain of volcanic mountains and associated highlands running the length of Java kept its interior regions and peoples separate and relatively isolated.&lt;ref&gt;Ricklefs (1991), pp. 16–17.&lt;/ref&gt; Before the advent of Islamic states and European colonialism, the rivers provided the main means of communication, although Java's many rivers are mostly short. Only the [[Brantas River|Brantas]] and Sala rivers could provide long-distance communication, and this way their valleys supported the centres of major kingdoms. A system of roads, permanent bridges and toll gates is thought to have been established in Java by at least the mid-17th century. Local powers could disrupt the routes as could the wet season and road use was highly dependent on constant maintenance. Subsequently, communication between Java's population was difficult.&lt;ref&gt;Ricklefs (1991), p. 15.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Hindu-Buddhist kingdoms era===
[[File:Prambanan Trimurti.jpg|thumb| [[Prambanan]] Hindu temple]]
[[File:Borobudur-Temple-Park Indonesia Stupas-of-Borobudur-04.jpg|thumb|The 9th century [[Borobudur]] Buddhist [[stupa]] in Central Java]]The [[Tarumanagara|Taruma]] and [[Sunda kingdom|Sunda]] kingdoms of western Java appeared in the 4th and 7th centuries respectively, while the [[Kalingga Kingdom]] sent embassies to China starting in 640.&lt;ref name=Coedes&gt;{{cite book|last= Coedès|first= George|authorlink= George Coedès|editor= Walter F. Vella|others= trans.Susan Brown Cowing|title= The Indianized States of Southeast Asia|year= 1968|publisher= University of Hawaii Press|isbn= 978-0-8248-0368-1}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{rp|53,79}} However, the first major principality was the [[Medang Kingdom]] that was founded in central Java at the beginning of the 8th century. Medang's religion centred on the Hindu god [[Shiva]], and the kingdom produced some of Java's earliest Hindu temples on the [[Dieng Plateau]]. Around the 8th century the [[Sailendra]] dynasty rose in [[Kedu Plain]] and become the patron of [[Mahayana]] [[Buddhism]]. This ancient kingdom built monuments such as the 9th century [[Borobudur]] and [[Prambanan]] in central Java.

Around the 10th century the centre of power shifted from central to eastern Java. The eastern Javanese kingdoms of [[Kediri (historical kingdom)|Kediri]], [[Singhasari]] and [[Majapahit]] were mainly dependent on rice agriculture, yet also pursued trade within the Indonesian archipelago, and with China and India.

[[Majapahit]] was established by [[Raden Wijaya|Wijaya]]&lt;ref name=Coedes/&gt;{{rp|201}} and by the end of the reign of [[Hayam Wuruk]] (r. 1350–89) it claimed sovereignty over the entire Indonesian archipelago, although control was likely limited to Java, Bali and Madura. Hayam Wuruk's prime minister, [[Gajah Mada]], led many of the kingdom's territorial conquests.&lt;ref name=Coedes/&gt;{{rp|234}} Previous Javanese kingdoms had their power based in agriculture, however, Majapahit took control of ports and shipping lanes and became Java's first commercial empire. With the death of Hayam Wuruk and the [[The spread of Islam in Indonesia|coming of Islam to Indonesia]], Majapahit went into decline.&lt;ref name=Coedes/&gt;{{rp|241}}

===Spread of Islam and rise of Islamic sultanates===
[[Islam]] became the dominant religion in Java at the end of the 16th century. During this era, the Islamic kingdoms of [[Demak Sultanate|Demak]], [[Sultanate of Cirebon|Cirebon]], and [[Banten Sultanate|Banten]] were ascendant. The [[Mataram Sultanate]] became the dominant power of central and eastern Java at the end of the 16th century. The principalities of Surabaya and Cirebon were eventually subjugated such that only Mataram and Banten were left to face the Dutch in the 17th century.

===Colonial periods===
[[File:COLLECTIE TROPENMUSEUM Thee-kweekbedden zonder afdak Java TMnr 10011931.jpg|thumb|Tea plantation in Java during [[Dutch East Indies|Dutch colonial period]], in or before 1926]]

Java's contact with the European colonial powers began in 1522 with [[Luso Sundanese Treaty|a treaty]] between the [[Sunda kingdom]] and the [[Portuguese Malacca|Portuguese in Malacca]]. After its failure the [[The Portuguese in Indonesia|Portuguese presence]] was confined to Malacca, and to the eastern islands.
In 1596, a four-ship expedition led by [[Cornelis de Houtman]] was the first Dutch contact with Indonesia.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=The Globe Encompassed: The Age of European Discovery, 1500–1700|author=Ames, Glenn J.|year=2008|page=99}}&lt;/ref&gt; By the end of the 18th century the Dutch had extended their influence over the sultanates of the interior through the [[Dutch East India Company in Indonesia]]. Internal conflict prevented the Javanese from forming effective alliances against the Dutch. Remnants of the Mataram survived as the Surakarta (Solo) and Yogyakarta principalities. Javanese kings claimed to rule with divine authority and the Dutch helped them to preserve remnants of a Javanese aristocracy by confirming them as regents or district officials within the colonial administration.

Java's major role during the early part of the colonial period was as a producer of [[rice]]. In spice producing islands like [[Banda Islands|Banda]], rice was regularly imported from Java, to supply the deficiency in means of subsistence.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=St. John|first=Horace Stebbing Roscoe|title=The Indian Archipelago: its history and present state, Volume 1|publisher=Longman, Brown, Green, and Longmans|year=1853 |page=137|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=UJ9FAAAAIAAJ}}&lt;/ref&gt;

During the [[Napoleonic wars]] in Europe, the [[Netherlands]] fell to [[France]], as did its colony in the [[East Indies]]. During the short-lived [[Daendels]] administration, as French proxy rule on Java, the construction of the [[Great Post Road|Java Great Post Road]] was commenced in 1808. The road, spanning from [[Anyer]] in Western Java to Panarukan in East Java, served as a military supply route and was used in defending Java from British invasion.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=Ekspedisi Anjer-Panaroekan, Laporan Jurnalistik Kompas|publisher=Pnerbit Buku Kompas, PT Kompas Media Nusantara, Jakarta Indonesia|date=November 2008|pages=1–2|ISBN=978-979-709-391-4}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1811, Java was [[Invasion of Java (1811)|captured by the British]], becoming a possession of the [[British Empire]], and Sir [[Stamford Raffles]] was appointed as the island's Governor. In 1814, Java was returned to the Dutch under the terms of the [[Treaty of Paris (1814)|Treaty of Paris]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Atkins|first=James|title=The Coins And Tokens Of The Possessions And Colonies Of The British Empire|year=1889&lt;!--|location=Quaritch, Bernard--&gt;|location=London|page=213}}&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:The Allied Occupation of Java, 1945 SE4857.jpg|thumb|Japanese prepare to discuss surrender terms with British-allied forces in Java 1945]]

In 1815, there may have been five million people in Java.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.britannica.com/EBchecked/topic/301673/Java Java (island, Indonesia)]. Encyclopædia Britannica.&lt;/ref&gt; In the second half of the 18th century, population spurts began in districts along the north-central coast of Java, and in the 19th century population grew rapidly across the island. Factors for the great population growth include the impact of Dutch colonial rule including the imposed end to civil war in Java, the increase in the area under rice cultivation, and the introduction of food plants such as [[casava]] and [[maize]] that could sustain populations that could not afford rice.&lt;ref&gt;Taylor (2003), p. 253.&lt;/ref&gt; Others attribute the growth to the taxation burdens and increased expansion of employment under the [[Cultivation System]] to which couples responded by having more children in the hope of increasing their families' ability to pay tax and buy goods.&lt;ref&gt;Taylor (2003), pp. 253–254.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Cholera]] claimed 100,000 lives in Java in 1820.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|first=Joseph Patrick|last=Byrne|title=Encyclopedia of Pestilence, Pandemics, and Plagues: A-M|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=5Pvi-ksuKFIC&amp;pg=PA99&amp;dq#v=onepage&amp;q=&amp;f=false|publisher=ABC-CLIO|year=2008|page=99|isbn=0-313-34102-8}}
&lt;/ref&gt;

The advent of trucks and railways where there had previously only been buffalo and carts, telegraph systems, and more coordinated distribution systems under the colonial government all contributed to famine elimination in Java, and in turn, population growth. There were no significant famines in Java from the 1840s through to the [[Japanese occupation of Indonesia|Japanese occupation]] in the 1940s.&lt;ref name=&quot;Taylor 2003, p. 254&quot;&gt;Taylor (2003), p. 254.&lt;/ref&gt; Furthermore, the age of first marriage dropped during the 19th century thus increasing a woman's child bearing years.&lt;ref name=&quot;Taylor 2003, p. 254&quot;/&gt;

===Independence===
{{main|Indonesian National Awakening}}

Indonesian nationalism first took hold in Java in the early 20th century, and [[Indonesian National Revolution|the struggle to secure the country's independence]] following [[World War II]] was centered in Java. In 1949, Indonesia became independent and the island has dominated Indonesian social, political and economic life, which has been the source of resentment of those residents in other islands.

==Demography==

===Demographic profile===
[[File:Jakarta.jpg|left|thumb|[[Jakarta]], the capital of [[Indonesia]] ]]
{{Historical populations
|1971 | 76086320
|1980 | 91269528
|1990 | 107581306	
|2000 | 121352608
|2010 | 136610590
|2015 | 145013583
|footnote=sources:&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bps.go.id/tab_sub/view.php?kat=1&amp;tabel=1&amp;daftar=1&amp;id_subyek=12&amp;notab=1|title=Statistics Indonesia|website=Bps.go.id|accessdate=17 July 2013|archivedate=1 July 2013 |archiveurl=//web.archive.org/web/20130701144756/http://www.bps.go.id/tab_sub/view.php?kat=1&amp;tabel=1&amp;daftar=1&amp;id_subyek=12&amp;notab=1}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=kemenkesehat/&gt; refers to the administrative region}}

Java has been traditionally demographically dominated by an elite class, while the masses remained agriculturally and fishing bound and thus were sustained by high birthrates.  This elite class has changed over the course of history, as cultural waves after waves lapped the island. There is evidence that South Asian emigres were among this elite, as well as Arabian and Persian immigrants during the Islamic eras.  More recently, Chinese have become part of the economic elite of Java, although politically they generally remain sidelined, there are notable exceptions such as the governor of Jakarta, [[Basuki Tjahaja Purnama]]. Today, Java is increasingly urban, modern culture has arrived in Java, yet only 75% of the island is electrified, villages and their rice paddies still are a common sight, as well as well as a youthful population. Central Java unlike the rest of the island registers very slow population growth, yet it maintains a more youthful population than the national average,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bkkbn.go.id/kependudukan/Pages/DataSensus/Sensus_Penduduk/Pola_Perkawinan/Rata_Usia_Kawin_Pertama/Nasional.aspx Usia Kawin Pertama Rata-Rata Wanita  Menurut Provinsi: Sensus Penduduk Tahun 1990, 2000 dan 2010]. Retrieved 16 August 2015.&lt;/ref&gt; this is explained by heavy outflows from the countryside or from lesser cities in search of larger incomes as the region remains economically depressed.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.thejakartapost.com/news/2009/03/30/central-java-strives-alleviate-poverty.html|author=Agus Maryono|title=Central Java strives to alleviate poverty|work=The Jakarta Post|date=30 March 2009|accessdate=16 August 2015|archivedate=8 September 2015|archiveurl=//web.archive.org/web/20150908234750/http://www.thejakartapost.com/news/2009/03/30/central-java-strives-alleviate-poverty.html}}&lt;/ref&gt; Java's population continues to relentlessly increase despite masses of Javans leaving, the island is the business academic and cultural hub of the nation and therefore attracts millions of non-Javans to its cities, the inflows are most intense in regions surrounding [[Jakarta]] and [[Bandung]] and diversity of demographics reflect this in those areas.

===Population development===
With a combined population of 145 million in the 2015 census (including Madura's 3.7 million),&lt;ref name=JKTPOS&gt;{{cite news|title=Population growth 'good for Papua'|date=23 August 2010|accessdate=30 August 2010|url= http://www.thejakartapost.com/news/2010/08/23/population-growth-%E2%80%98good-papua%E2%80%99.html|work=[[The Jakarta Post]]|archivedate=24 August 2010|archiveurl=//web.archive.org/web/20100824053746/http://www.thejakartapost.com/news/2010/08/23/population-growth-%E2%80%98good-papua%E2%80%99.html}}&lt;/ref&gt; which is estimated for 2014 at 143.1 million (including 3.7 million for Madura), Java is the [[List of islands by population|most populous island in the world]] and is home to 57% of Indonesia's population.&lt;ref name=&quot;JKTPOS&quot;/&gt; At over 1,100 people per km² in 2014, it is also one of the most densely populated parts of the world, on par with Bangladesh. Every region of the island has numerous volcanoes, with the people left to share the remaining flatter land. Because of this, many coasts are heavily populated and cities ring around the valleys surrounding volcanic peaks. Thus the [[physiological density]] of Java is exceptionally high, even by Asian standards.{{or|date=October 2015}}

Notably, population growth rate more than doubled in economically depressed Central Java in the latest 2010-2015 period vs 2000-2010, indicative of migration or other issues, there were significant [[Mount Merapi#2006 eruption|volcanic eruption]]s during the earlier period.  Approximately 45% of the population of Indonesia is ethnically Javanese,&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.cia.gov/library/publications/the-world-factbook/geos/id.html CIA factbook]&lt;/ref&gt; while Sundanese make a large portion of Java's population as well.

The western third of the island (West Java, Banten, and DKI Jakarta) has an even higher population density, of nearly 1,500 per square kilometer and accounts for the lion's share of the population growth of Java.&lt;ref name=&quot;JKTPOS&quot;/&gt; It is home to three metropolitan areas, [[Greater Jakarta]] (with outlying areas of Greater [[Serang]] and Greater [[Sukabumi]]), [[Bandung Metropolitan Area|Greater Bandung]], and Greater [[Cirebon]].

{| class=&quot;wikitable sortable&quot;
|-
! Province or Special Region
! Capital
! Area&lt;br /&gt;km²
! Area&lt;br /&gt;%
! Population&lt;br /&gt;[[census]] of 2000&lt;ref name=&quot;citypop&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.citypopulation.de/Indonesia-MU.html |title=Indonesia (Urban City Population): Provinces &amp; Cities - Statistics &amp; Maps on City Population |publisher=Citypopulation.de |date=2010-05-01 |accessdate=2013-07-17}}&lt;/ref&gt;
! Population&lt;br /&gt;census of 2010&lt;ref name=&quot;citypop&quot;/&gt;
! Population&lt;br /&gt;2015 census (prelim.)&lt;ref name=&quot;citypopulation.de&quot;/&gt;
! Population&lt;br /&gt;density in 2015
|-
| [[Banten]]
| [[Serang]]
| style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot;|9,662.92
| style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot;|7.1
| style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot;|8,098,277
| style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot;|10,632,166
| style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot;|11,934,373
| style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot;|1,235
|-
| [[DKI Jakarta]]
| -
| style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot;|664.01
| style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot;|0.5
| style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot;|8,361,079
| style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot;|9,607,787
| style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot;|10,154,134
| style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot;|15,292
|-
| [[West Java]]
| [[Bandung]]
| style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot;|35,377.76
| style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot;|27.1
| style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot;|35,724,093
| style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot;|43,053,732
| style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot;|46,668,224
| style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot;|1,319
|-
| ''Western Java &lt;br&gt;(3 areas above)''
| 
| style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot;|''45,704.69''
| style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot;|''34.7''
| style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot;|''52,183,449''
| style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot;|''63,293,685''
| style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot;|''68,756,731''
| style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot;|''1,504''
|-
| [[Central Java]]
| [[Semarang]]
| style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot;|32,800.69
| style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot;|25.3
| style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot;|31,223,258
| style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot;|32,382,657
| style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot;|33,753,023
| style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot;|1,029
|-
| [[Yogyakarta Special Region|Yogyakarta]]
| [[Yogyakarta]]
| style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot;|3,133.15
| style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot;|2.4
| style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot;|3,121,045
| style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot;|3,457,491
| style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot;|3,675,768
| style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot;|1,173
|-
| ''Central Java Region&lt;br&gt;(2 areas above)''
| 
| style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot;|''35,933.84''
| style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot;|''27.7''
| style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot;|''34,344,303''
| style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot;|''35,840,148''
| style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot;|''37,428,791''
| style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot;|''1,041''
|-
| [[East Java]]
| [[Surabaya]]
| style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot;|47,799.75
| style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot;|37.3
| style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot;|34,765,993
| style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot;|37,476,757
| style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot;|38,828,061
| style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot;|812
|-
| Region Administered as ''Java''
| [[Jakarta]]
| style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot;|129,438.28
| style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot;|100%
| style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot;|121,293,745
| style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot;|136,610,590
| style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot;|145,013,583
| style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot;|1,120
|-
|
:[[Madura]] Island of East Java
| -
| style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot;|5,025.30
| style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot;|3.3
| style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot;|3,230,300
| style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot;|3,622,763
| style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot;|3,724,545**
| style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot;|741**
|-
|
:Java Island&lt;sup&gt;1)&lt;/sup&gt;
| -
| style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot;|124,412.98
| style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot;|96.7
| style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot;|118,063,445
| style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot;|132,987,827
| style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot;|141,300,000**
| style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot;|1,136**
|}
&lt;sup&gt;1) Other islands are included in this figure, but are very small in population and area, Nusa Barung 100&amp;nbsp;km², Bawean 196&amp;nbsp;km², Karimunjawa 78&amp;nbsp;km², Kambangan 121&amp;nbsp;km², Panaitan 170&amp;nbsp;km², Thousand Islands 8.7&amp;nbsp;km² - with a combined population of roughly 90,000.&lt;/sup&gt;

&lt;sup&gt;2) Land area of provinces updated in 2010 Census figures, areas may be different than past results.&lt;/sup&gt;

&lt;sup&gt;3) 2015 Census prelim data released only first level administrations only, where not available 2014 [[Ministry of Health (Indonesia)|Min. Health]]&lt;ref name=kemenkesehat&gt;{{cite web|format=PDF|accessdate=20 February 2014|url=http://www.depkes.go.id/downloads/Penduduk%20Kab%20Kota%20Umur%20Tunggal%202014.pdf|title=Estimasi Penduduk Menurut Umur Tunggal Dan Jenis Kelamin 2014 Kementerian Kesehatan|archivedate=20 February 2014|archiveurl=//web.archive.org/web/20140208021950/http://depkes.go.id/downloads/Penduduk%20Kab%20Kota%20Umur%20Tunggal%202014.pdf}}&lt;/ref&gt; estimates are used in their place.&lt;/sup&gt;

From the 1970s to the fall of the [[Suharto]] regime in 1998, the Indonesian government ran [[transmigration program]]s aimed at resettling the population of Java on other less-populated islands of Indonesia. This program has met with mixed results, sometimes causing conflicts between the locals and the recently arrived [[settler]]s. Nevertheless, it has caused Java's share of the nation's population to progressively decline.

Jakarta and its outskirts, being the dominant metropolis, is also home to people from all over the nation. East Java is also home to ethnic Balinese, as well as large numbers of Madurans due to their historic poverty.

===Ethnicity and culture===
{{See also|Culture of Indonesia|Music of Java}}
[[File:COLLECTIE TROPENMUSEUM Een jonge Javaan te Semarang Java TMnr 10002811.jpg|thumb|180px|left|A teenager in Java wearing traditional [[Javanese people|Javanese]] attire: [[blangkon]] headgear, [[batik]] sarong and [[kris]] as accessory. 1913]]
[[File:Gamelandegung.jpg|thumb|[[Sundanese people|Sundanese]] [[Gamelan]] players]]
[[File:Ramayana Java.jpg|thumb|right|[[Lakshmana]], [[Rama]] and [[Sita|Shinta]] in [[Ramayana]] ballet at [[Prambanan]], Java.]]
Despite its large population and in contrast to the other larger islands of Indonesia, Java is comparatively homogeneous in ethnic composition. Only two ethnic groups are native to the island—the [[Javanese people|Javanese]] and [[Sundanese people|Sundanese]]. A third group is the [[Madurese people|Madurese]], who inhabit the island of [[Madura Island|Madura]] off the north east coast of Java, and have immigrated to [[East Java]] in large numbers since the 18th century.&lt;ref name=Periplus58&gt;{{cite book|last=Hefner|first=Robert|title=Java|publisher=Periplus Editions|year=1997|location=Singapore|page=58|isbn=962-593-244-5}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Javanese comprise about two-thirds of the island's population, while the Sundanese and Madurese account for 20% and 10% respectively.&lt;ref name=Periplus58/&gt; The fourth group is the [[Betawi people]] that speak a dialect of [[Malay language|Malay]], they are the descendants of the people living around [[Jakarta|Batavia]] from around the 17th century. Betawis are [[creole people]], mostly descended from various Indonesian archipelago ethnic groups such as [[Ethnic Malay|Malay]], [[Sundanese people|Sundanese]], [[Javanese people|Javanese]], [[Balinese people|Balinese]], [[Minangkabau people|Minang]], [[Bugis people|Bugis]], [[Makassar people|Makassar]], [[Ambonese]], mixed with foreign ethnic groups such as [[Portuguese people|Portuguese]], [[Dutch people|Dutch]], [[Arab]], [[Chinese people|Chinese]] and [[Indian peoples|Indian]] brought to or attracted to Batavia to meet labour needs. They have a culture and language distinct from the surrounding [[Sundanese people|Sundanese]] and [[Javanese people|Javanese]].

The Javanese [[kakawin]] [[Tantu Pagelaran]] explained the mythical origin of the island and its volcanic nature. Four major cultural areas exist on the island: the ''[[Javanese beliefs|kejawen]]'' or Javanese heartland, the north coast of the ''pasisir'' region, the [[Sundanese people|Sunda]] lands of West Java, and the eastern salient, also known as [[Banyuwangi|Blambangan]]. Madura makes up a fifth area having close cultural ties with coastal Java.&lt;ref name=Periplus58/&gt; The ''kejawen'' Javanese culture is the island's most dominant. Java's remaining aristocracy are based here, and it is the region from where the majority of Indonesia's army, business, and political elite originate. Its language, arts, and etiquette are regarded as the island's most refined and exemplary.&lt;ref name=Periplus58/&gt; The territory from [[Banyumas Regency|Banyumas]] in the west through to [[Blitar]] in the east and encompasses Indonesia's most fertile and densely populated agricultural land.&lt;ref name=Periplus58/&gt;

In the southwestern part of Central Java, which is usually named the [[Banyumas Regency|Banyumasan]] region, a cultural mingling occurred; bringing together Javanese culture and Sundanese culture to create the [[Banyumasan language|Banyumasan]] culture.{{Citation needed|date=June 2009}} In the central Javanese court cities of [[Yogyakarta (city)|Yogyakarta]] and [[Surakarta]], contemporary kings trace their lineages back to the pre-colonial Islamic kingdoms that ruled the region, making those places especially strong repositories of classical Javanese culture. Classic arts of Java include [[gamelan]] music and [[wayang]] puppet shows.

Java was the site of many influential kingdoms in the Southeast Asian region,&lt;ref&gt;See Wallace Stevens's poem &quot;[[Tea (poem)|Tea]]&quot; for an appreciative allusion to Javanese culture.&lt;/ref&gt; and as a result, many literary works have been written by Javanese authors. These include ''[[Ken Arok]] and [[Ken Dedes]]'', the story of the orphan who usurped his king, and married the queen of the ancient Javanese kingdom; and translations of ''[[Ramayana]]'' and ''[[Mahabharata]]''. [[Pramoedya Ananta Toer]] is a famous contemporary Indonesian author, who has written many stories based on his own experiences of having grown up in Java, and takes many elements from Javanese folklore and historical legends.

===Languages===
[[File:Java languages.JPG|thumb|220px|Languages spoken in Java (Javanese is shown in white). &quot;Malay&quot; refers to [[Betawi language|Betawi]], the local dialect as one of Malay creole dialect.]]

The three major languages spoken on Java are [[Javanese language|Javanese]], [[Sundanese language|Sundanese]] and [[Madurese language|Madurese]]. Other languages spoken include [[Betawi language|Betawi]] (a [[Malay language|Malay]] dialect local to the Jakarta region), [[Osing language|Osing]], [[Banyumasan language|Banyumasan]], and [[Tenggerese]] (closely related to Javanese), [[Baduy]] (closely related to Sundanese), [[Kangean language|Kangean]]ese (closely related to Madurese), and [[Balinese language|Balinese]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ethnologue.com/show_country.asp?name=Indonesia+(Java+and+Bali) Languages of Java and Bali] – Ethnologue. Other sources may list some of these as dialects rather than languages.&lt;/ref&gt; The vast majority of the population also speaks [[Indonesian language|Indonesian]], often as a second language.

===Religion===
[[File:Pura Parahyangan Agung Jagatkartta, Candi Siliwangi Shrine.jpg|thumb|A [[Hindu]] shrine dedicated to [[King Siliwangi]] in Pura Parahyangan Agung Jagatkartta, [[Bogor]], West Java.]]
[[File:COLLECTIE TROPENMUSEUM Moskee Indonesië TMnr 10016740.jpg|thumb|Mosque in Pati, Central Java, during [[Dutch East Indies|colonial period]]. The mosque combined traditional Javanese style (multi-tiered roof) with European architecture.]]
{{main|Religion in Indonesia}}

Java has been a melting pot of religions and cultures, which has created a broad range of religious belief.

[[South Asia|Indian]] influences came first with [[Shaivism]] and [[Buddhism]] penetrating deeply into society, blending with indigenous tradition and culture.&lt;ref name=&quot;kroef1961&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|first=Justus M.|last=van der Kroef|title=New Religious Sects in Java|journal=Far Eastern Survey|volume=30|issue=2|year=1961|pages=18–15|doi=10.1525/as.1961.30.2.01p1432u|jstor=3024260}}&lt;/ref&gt; One [[Conduit (spiritualism)|conduit]] for this were the [[asceticism|ascetic]]s, called ''resi'', who taught mystical practices. A ''resi'' lived surrounded by students, who took care of their master's daily needs. Resi's authorities were merely ceremonial. At the courts, [[Brahmin]] clerics and ''pudjangga'' (sacred literati) legitimised rulers and linked [[Hinduism|Hindu]] cosmology to their political needs.&lt;ref name=&quot;kroef1961&quot;/&gt; Small [[Hindu]] enclaves are scattered throughout Java, but there is a large [[Hindu]] population along the eastern coast nearest [[Bali]], especially around the town of [[Banyuwangi]].

[[Islam]], which came after Hinduism, strengthened the status structure of this traditional religious pattern. More than 90 percent of the people of Java are Muslims, on a broad continuum between ''[[abangan]]'' (more traditional) and ''[[santri]]'' (more modernist). The Muslim scholar of the writ (''[[Kyai]]'') became the new religious elite as Hindu influences receded. Islam recognises no hierarchy of religious leaders nor a formal [[Clergy|priesthood]], but the [[Dutch East India Company|Dutch colonial government]] established an elaborate rank order for mosque and other Islamic preaching schools. In Javanese ''[[pesantren]]'' (Islamic schools), The ''Kyai'' perpetuated the tradition of the ''resi''. Students around him provided his needs, even [[peasant]]s around the school.&lt;ref name=&quot;kroef1961&quot;/&gt;

Pre-Islamic Javan traditions have encouraged Islam in a mystical direction. There emerged in Java a loosely structured society of religious leadership, revolving around ''kyais'', possessing various degrees of proficiency in pre-Islamic and Islamic [[Folklore|lore]], [[belief]] and practice.&lt;ref name=&quot;kroef1961&quot;/&gt; The kyais are the principal intermediaries between the villages masses and the realm of the [[supernatural]]. However, this very looseneess of kyai leadership structure has promoted [[schism (religion)|schism]]. There were often sharp divisions between orthodox kyais, who merely instructed in Islamic law, with those who taught [[mysticism]] and those who sought reformed Islam with modern scientific concepts. As a result, there is a division between ''santri'', who believe that they are more orthodox in their Islamic belief and practice, with ''[[abangan]]'', who have mixed pre-Islamic [[animism|animistic]] and Hindu-Indian concepts with a superficial acceptance of Islamic belief.&lt;ref name=&quot;kroef1961&quot;/&gt;

There are also [[Christian]] communities, mostly in the larger cities, though some rural areas of south-central Java are strongly [[Catholic Church|Roman Catholic]]. [[Buddhism|Buddhist]] communities also exist in the major cities, primarily among the [[Chinese Indonesian]]. The Indonesian constitution recognises six official religions.

A wider effect of this division is the number of sects. In the middle of 1956, the Department of Religious Affairs in [[Yogyakarta]] reported 63 religious sects in Java other than the official Indonesian religions. Of these, 35 were in [[Central Java]], 22 in [[West Java]] and six in [[East Java]].&lt;ref name=&quot;kroef1961&quot;/&gt; These include [[Javanese beliefs|Kejawen]], [[Javanese beliefs|Sumarah]], [[Subud]], etc. Their total membership is difficult to estimate as many of their adherents identify themselves with one of the official religions.&lt;ref name=&quot;Beatty&quot;&gt;Beatty, Andrew, ''Varieties of Javanese Religion: An Anthropological Account'', Cambridge University Press 1999, ISBN 0-521-62473-8&lt;/ref&gt;

==Economy==
[[File:KerbauJawa.jpg|left|thumb|[[Water buffalo|Water Buffalo]] ploughing [[Paddy field|rice fields]] near [[Salatiga]], [[Central Java]]]]
Initially the economy of Java relied heavily on [[rice]] agriculture. Ancient kingdoms such as the [[Tarumanagara]], [[Mataram Kingdom|Mataram]], and [[Majapahit]] were dependent on rice yields and tax. Java was famous for rice surpluses and rice export since ancient times, and rice agriculture contributed to the population growth of the island. Trade with other parts of Asia such as India and China flourished as early as the 4th century, as evidenced by Chinese ceramics found on the island dated to that period. Java also took part in the global trade of [[Maluku Islands|Maluku]] [[spice]] from ancient times in the Majapahit era, until well into the [[Dutch East India Company|VOC]] era.

[[Dutch East India Company]] set their foothold on [[Batavia, Dutch East Indies|Batavia]] in the 17th century and was succeeded by [[Netherlands East Indies]] in the 19th century. During these colonial times, the Dutch introduced the cultivation of commercial plants in Java, such as [[sugarcane]], [[rubber]], [[coffee]], [[tea]], and [[quinine]]. In the 19th and early 20th century, Javanese coffee gained global popularity. Thus, the name &quot;Java&quot; today has become a synonym for coffee.

[[File:Java Transportation Network.svg|thumb|right|250px|Java transportation network]]
[[File:Jakarta Car Free Day.jpg|thumb|Central [[Jakarta]]]]
Java is the most developed island in Indonesia since the era of Netherlands East Indies to modern Republic of Indonesia. The road transportation networks that have existed since ancient times were connected and perfected with the construction of [[Great Post Road|Java Great Post Road]] by [[Daendels]] in the early 19th century. The Java Great Post Road become the backbone of Java's road infrastructure and laid the base of [[North Coast Road (Java)|Java North Coast Road]] ({{lang-id|Jalan Pantura, abbreviation from &quot;Pantai Utara&quot;}}). The need to transport commercial produces such as coffee from plantations in the interior of the island to the harbour on the coast spurred the construction of railway networks in Java. Today the [[industry]], business and trade, also services flourished in major cities of Java, such as [[Jakarta]], [[Surabaya]], [[Semarang]], and [[Bandung]]; while some traditional Sultanate cities such as [[Yogyakarta]], [[Surakarta]], and [[Cirebon]] preserved its royal legacy and become the centre of art, culture and tourism in Java. Industrial estates also growing in towns on northern coast of Java, especially around [[Cilegon]], [[Tangerang]], [[Bekasi]], [[Karawang]], [[Gresik]] and [[Sidoarjo]]. The [[toll road]] highway networks was built and expanded since [[Suharto]] era until now, connecting major urban centres and surrounding areas, such as in and around [[Jakarta]] and [[Bandung]]; also the ones in [[Cirebon]], [[Semarang]] and [[Surabaya]]. In addition to these motorways, Java has 16 national highways.

Based on the statistical data by the year of 2012 which's released by Badan Pusat Statistik, Java Island itself contributes at least 57.51% of Indonesia's Gross Domestic Product or equivalent to 504 billion US Dollars.

==See also==
{{Portal|Indonesia}}
*[[History of Indonesia]]
*[[List of monarchs of Java]]

==References==
{{Reflist|2}}

==Sources==
{{refbegin}}
*{{cite book|last=Taylor|first=Jean Gelman|title=Indonesia: Peoples and Histories|publisher=Yale University Press|year=2003|location=New Haven and London|isbn=0-300-10518-5}}
{{refend}}

==Further reading==
*{{cite book|last=Cribb|first=Robert|title=Historical Atlas of Indonesia|publisher=RoutledgeCurzon Press, University of Hawaii Press|year=2000|location=London and Honolulu|isbn=0-8248-2111-4}}

==External links==
{{Commons and category|Java|Java}}
{{wikivoyage|Java}}

{{Indonesia}}

{{Authority control}}

[[Category:Java| ]]
[[Category:Greater Sunda Islands]]
[[Category:Islands of Indonesia]]
[[Category:Maritime Southeast Asia]]</text>
      <sha1>rv4wp8mplk8sqmqic6p6fx6hbbq77ns</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Undefined</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>42727860</id>
    <revision>
      <id>733481463</id>
      <parentid>733481364</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-08-08T03:37:04Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Moriori</username>
        <id>26606</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Reverted edits by [[Special:Contribs/223.104.91.93|223.104.91.93]] ([[User talk:223.104.91.93|talk]]) to last version by Nyuszika7H</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="1037">{{wiktionary}}
'''Undefined''' refers to something that lacks [[definition]].

'''Undefined''' may also refer to:
{{tocright}}
==Mathematics==
* [[Undefined (mathematics)]], with several related meanings
* [[Indeterminate form]], in calculus

==Computing==
* [[Undefined behavior]], computer code whose behavior is not specified under certain conditions
* [[Undefined value]], a condition where an expression does not have a correct value
* Undefined, a function or variable lacking [[declaration (computer programming)|declaration]]
* Undefined, a variable lacking [[initialization (programming)|initialisation]]
* Undefined, an unavailable linker symbol (function, or global variable); see [[dynamic linker]]

==Other uses==
* [[Undefined citizenship]], a term used in Estonia to denote a post-Soviet form of statelessness

==See also==
* [[Null (disambiguation)]]
* [[Void (disambiguation)]]
* [[Invalid (disambiguation)]]
* [[Definition (disambiguation)]]
* [[Definable (disambiguation)]]
* {{lookfrom|Undefined}}

{{disambiguation}}</text>
      <sha1>kjl8gya5rmf1u9ce0ym67kxwlhx93z7</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
